Hey guys, quick note before we get into
the video. I've been pretty busy moving
between states and working on my
startup, Silo. So, my brother is filling
in for me on this video. Let me know
what you think in the comments. With
that out of the way, let's get right
into it.
>> In 2024, Nintendo launched a major
lawsuit over a game that seemed like a
pretty clear Pokémon rip-off, but they
probably didn't expect it to backfire so
bad. Most of their new patents are being
rejected, and the most they can win is
just $30,000.
But, this gets even weirder. Why does
everyone, including Nintendo's own
customers, seem to be on the side of the
copycat? Maybe the story isn't so black
and white.
Pokémon is, by far, the largest media
franchise on Earth. Seriously.
To date, it's made well over $115
billion
in revenue. Few entertainment franchises
even come close. That's more than Star
Wars, the MCU, and Harry Potter. More
than any two of those combined, too.
Pokémon is a behemoth, but it's not just
the games that make it a cash cow, but
all of the merchandise from those iconic
designs. Given the absurd money this
brand makes, Nintendo are fairly
protective of it. Which might explain
their reaction to Pal World. On June
5th, 2021, developer Pocketpair revealed
a trailer for Pal World.
It showed a world where players can use
animal-like creatures called Pals to
battle and capture in order to use them
for base building, traversal, and
combat. This feels pretty familiar to
Pokémon. Some of these have pretty clear
or blatant inspirations. To even capture
characters, they have to be weakened and
thrown into a sphere similar to the Poké
Ball used in Pokémon. Though, there was
a big difference. Unlike Pokémon, Pals
can carry guns as well as work in large
ethically questionable factories.
Palworld was clearly going for a more
adult audience, and the trailer racked
up millions of views very quick. Some
viewers thought the game was fake, while
others labeled it Pokémon with guns.
Even IGN labeled the trailer a
Pokémon-like shooter game. The internet
was flooded with people calling out the
developers. Any delay of action by
Pokémon is just them building their
case. They're a $65 billion company that
got small fan-made content when it
infringes, even though it's free and
made for fun.
But, it definitely wasn't one-sided.
Regardless, things were fairly quiet for
now.
Though, in the background, Nintendo were
preparing for war.
Then, at last, in 2024, Palworld
launched in early access. Within 4
weeks, 25 million players had bought the
game. It made Steam history, becoming
the first game since PUBG to exceed 2
million concurrent players. This crashed
the servers.
Even today, Palworld still holds the
third largest all-time record for the
most players online simultaneously on
Steam, the largest video game
marketplace. This led to a deal between
Sony Music Entertainment, [music]
Aniplex, and Pocket Pair to form
Palworld Entertainment to expand the IP.
Pocket Pair were on top of the world.
"Thank you so much for making us the
third highest concurrent played game on
Steam ever. We are working hard to make
the game as enjoyable as possible. Thank
you." CEO Takuro Mizobe also said
Palworld's launch was so big that the
company couldn't handle the massive
profits the game generated. But,
underneath the success was a brewing
backlash.
Almost every day, thousands of tweets
would discover new similarities between
Palworld and Pokémon. It got to a point
where CEO Takuro Mizobe called out
people who sent death threats to
Palworld's artists. All aspects of
production are supervised by various
people within the company. And I am
responsible for the overall production.
It would be appreciated if you could
cease sending abuse towards the artists.
People also began pointing out that the
first Pokémon game shares a lot of
designs with other game, Dragon Quest 5.
The discourse was growing.
Was it a copycat?
Then, at long last, Nintendo decided to
respond. We have received many inquiries
regarding another company's game
released in January 2024. We intend to
investigate and take appropriate
measures to address any acts that
infringe on intellectual property rights
related to Pokémon.
Nintendo prepared for a major lawsuit.
But, strangely, this lawsuit wasn't all
about these designs at all, but
something else entirely.
Nintendo's lawsuits centered on three
Japanese patents. JP7545191
and JP7493117
covering creature captures and release
mechanics, and JP7528390
covering real-time switching between
ridable companions.
Also, one notable US patent. But, these
are a bit weird. Palworld was revealed
on June 5th, 2021. These initial patents
were first filed in December 2021.
These were soon published in 2024 in the
US and Japan. The patent infringement
lawsuit was filed in Japan on September
18th, 2024.
They sought an injunction and damages on
the grounds that Palworld infringes
multiple patent rights.
Nintendo will continue to take necessary
actions against any infringements of its
intellectual property rights to protect
the intellectual property it has worked
hard to establish over the years.
Pocketpair addressed the lawsuit in an
official statement. At this moment, we
are unaware of the specific patents we
are accused of infringing upon and we
have not been notified of such details.
It is truly unfortunate that we will be
forced to allocate significant time to
matters unrelated to game development
due to this lawsuit. However, we will do
our utmost for our fans and to ensure
that indie game developers are not
hindered or discouraged from pursuing
their creative ideas. Looking only at
the headlines, Nintendo's lawsuit seemed
completely justified.
Instead, many fans turned on Nintendo.
Across YouTube, Reddit, and gaming
forums, people seemed to side with
Pocketpair. Hence, the record-shattering
sale in a matter of days.
There are two big reasons, both
connected and both important. For the
last decade, Pokémon has under-delivered
with each new release, and Palworld
seems to be filling the space left by
Nintendo's failures. First, its games
have become notably choppier with lower
frame rates and less polish to the point
where they're no longer keeping up with
the competition. Yet, despite all of
that, it still carried a premium price
tag. Many fans felt they were paying a
Pokémon tax, buying the name more than
the quality. The warning signs were
already there. In 2019, Sword and Shield
launched to heavy criticism with players
calling out its poor production quality,
which, by the way, still cost $60. And
if you want to increase the frame rate,
you will buy the newest console and pay
an extra 10 to 20 dollars.
It felt like Pokémon wasn't even trying.
But customers were still hungry for that
classic Pokémon experience, and Palworld
filled that void.
Palworld had a few technical issues,
too, but it was far smoother, stable,
modern, and sharp. It felt like someone
had finally decided to make a good
Pokémon game.
We shouldn't compare it to Pokémon. That
would be an insult to Palworld. It's
actually better than the last few
Pokémon games. And when Nintendo sued,
customers felt they were trying to
stifle innovation and competition more
than protect their IP.
Someone finally made a good Pokémon
game, and Nintendo tries to shut it
down?
What Nintendo is trying to do with the
three patents in suit of this
litigation, and possibly others that are
in the making, is to create a patent
thicket. A multiplicity of patents
sharing a common context in an attempt
to block all roads. What Nintendo wants
to achieve is that Palworld cannot be
Palworld because as long as its game
mechanics of capturing monsters is the
one it is, there will be some Nintendo
patent in Japan that stands in the way.
Roadblock after roadblock.
But by this point, Nintendo had become
known for taking anyone to court.
They lobbied US Congress to stop video
games being rented in stores like
Blockbuster, then sued Blockbuster for
photocopying Nintendo manuals. Nintendo
also went after console emulators. It
sued the developers of a Switch emulator
who settled for 2.4 million dollars and
shut their project down. They blocked
another, Dolphin, from being released on
Steam. Same with another called Ryujinx.
The owner of LoveRoms were ordered to
pay over 12 million dollars, and one
even got 3 years in prison and was left
with millions of dollars in debt. This
wasn't even Nintendo's first patent
lawsuit over gameplay mechanics. Back in
2018, it sued Japanese developer Colopl
over a virtual joystick in a mobile
game. Yeah, they also routinely go after
their own fans. They ordered a major
Smash Bros. eSports circuit to be shut
down despite the organizers being in
contact with Nintendo for 12 months.
Fan projects are consistently shut down.
Needless to say, Nintendo doesn't have a
great reputation around its legal
fights. And Palworld's case makes it
much worse.
It is a clear case of bullying. Nintendo
is a far older and larger company than
Pocketpair with extensive experience in
patent prosecution and patent
infringement litigation. If, however,
companies write patent applications that
are effectively just smoke screens, the
net effect is that companies monopolize
game rules. That would set a terrible
precedent for the [music] industry.
It's fair to call Nintendo the Disney of
gaming.
Which brings us back [music] to the
lawsuit.
In September 2025, the US patent was
approved. The main claims were for a sub
character to appear and be controlled
while fighting an enemy. And for the sub
character to automatically fight enemies
when it's somewhere else, not near the
player. But this one was especially
weird because of how quick it was
approved.
It essentially was waved through without
much pushback, which didn't happen.
Did Nintendo suddenly have an
uncontested monopoly over common ideas
and mechanics? Was everyone now beholden
to Nintendo?
If you've watched this far, you probably
enjoy our videos. So, consider
subscribing. Thanks.
At first, the lawsuit seemed to be going
exactly the way Nintendo wanted. Rather
than fight over every patent mechanic,
Pocketpair changed the game.
The studio removed the Pal Sphere
mechanic that resembled Pokémon's Poké
Ball. Even more surprisingly, pals could
no longer be used for gliding. Instead,
players had to use ordinary gliders, a
change many never expected to see.
Pocketpair later confirmed that these
changes were made because of the ongoing
lawsuit. Several other game mechanics
were also changed with this patch. As
many have speculated, these changes were
indeed a result of the ongoing
litigation. And we have had to make
certain compromises in order to avoid
disruptions to the development and
distribution of Palworld. But the big
battle was the patents. Pocketpair
presented a long list of prior art to
show invalidity of Nintendo's claims. A
long list of older games including Ark,
Zelda, Titanfall 2, Far Cry 5, Rune
Factory 5, and many more, arguing these
mechanics had existed for years. Then
something unexpected happened. In
October 2025, Japan's Patent Office
rejected one of Nintendo's key patent
applications, ruling that similar
mechanics had already appeared in games
that Pocketpair mentioned, notably Ark.
Hugely validating for Palworld. But it
got even worse for Nintendo. There was
quite an uproar about Nintendo trying to
patent all these game mechanics. In
November, the US Patent Office agreed to
re-examine one of Nintendo's patents, an
unusually rare decision. Since the
re-examination process was introduced in
1981, only about 175 out of roughly
15,000 requests had been approved. Upon
re-examination, it was rejected in March
2026.
All 26 claims were rejected. So, why?
Obviousness. Even if nobody did the
exact combination first, was it an
obvious step any competent designer
would take? Obviousness in this case is
a legal ground that prevents the
patenting of innovations that would have
been obvious to a person having ordinary
skill in the art at the time of filing.
Plus, patents exist to protect physical
innovations where copying is easy and
supply is limited. Games aren't like
that. The idea is a cheap part. Nobody
is going to buy a worse clone just
because it summons monsters the same
way.
Nintendo quietly narrowed its lawsuits
to older versions of Palworld after
Pocketpair updated the game. By
mid-2026, the lawsuits had entered its
final stage.
Then, another blow.
Another divisional application from
Nintendo, a monster catching patent, was
rejected by Japan's Patent Office. The
JPO pointed to a 2013 Pokémon fan game
as proof the idea lacked an innovative
step in Nintendo's patent application.
Nintendo formally and strongly objected
to this as this is a fan game, which
they believe infringed upon its
copyrights. And that it was merely a
video.
And, hilariously, the JPO sustained its
rejection because copyright has no
bearing on determining an innovative
step. The company stated, "Ash, Pikachu,
and Pokéball should properly be referred
to as a character infringing upon Ash, a
character infringing upon Pikachu, and a
character infringing upon Pokéball,
respectively. The mere possibility that
the reasons for rejection could be
subject to such an unreasonable
misunderstanding has no bearing on the
assessment of innovative step. If it was
impermissible for the reasons for
rejection to refer to character names,
then even at the cost of being
redundant, accuracy should take
precedence. In that case, the notice
would need to use cumbersome
descriptions such as
an object in the form of a small animal
instead of Pokémon, an object in the
form of a boy wearing a red cap instead
of Ash, an object in the form of a small
yellow animal instead of Pikachu.
However, even with such rephrasing, the
logical structure of the grounds for
refusal remains unchanged. Therefore,
this argument has no bearing on
determining inventive step. Seems the
JPO is getting a bit irritated at
Nintendo. But by now, many legal experts
believed Nintendo had already lost the
battle that mattered most. Nintendo had
virtually no chance of stopping the
current version of Palworld.
Even if Nintendo eventually won, Mueller
believed the company would likely
receive only around 5 million yen.
Roughly $30,000, a tiny amount for the
size of Nintendo or how much that they
must have spent on legal fees. As the
lawsuit was wrapping up, Palworld
finally launched 1.0, the fully finished
version of the game. And it felt like
2024 all over again.
The launch of Palworld 1.0 was a mass
success, rising back to 1 million
concurrent players. Though, they've also
added more pals, which [music] are
pretty blatantly similar to Pokémon. But
Pocket Pair also stuck to its original
$29.99 price despite the huge list of
added content. And they've now sold more
copies than almost any Pokémon title.
Granted, at a lower price. Meanwhile,
Nintendo appears to be moving in the
opposite direction with Pokémon games
becoming more expensive.
Maybe now Palworld has finally pushed
Nintendo to focus on making better
quality games. Even players are hoping,
too. I wouldn't be surprised if next
Pokémon is somehow will be one of the
best recent ones just to attract people
back. Also, wouldn't be surprised if
they change nothing because it sells
anyways. I've been curious if they're
unironically going to take some notes
from how Palworld did things and
incorporate some aspects into the
upcoming games. Patents are used to
protect innovation, but at a certain
point, they can be weaponized. To let a
company monopolize an idea which causes
it to get worse. I think this story
shows market correction. Pocket pair
weren't stealing customers. They were
serving them better. And that's the free
market doing its work. If you're
dissatisfied with one product, you go to
other businesses which will serve you
better. And that pushes the original
company to make better products. There's
another company under siege from
lawsuits. Though, the stakes are much
higher. Steam is a largest video game
distributor and it seems like everyone
is suing them with claims of them being
a monopoly.
Yet, customers absolutely love Steam.
Why are customers defending a monopoly?
Click here to learn the rest of the
story.
But until next time, I'm Shrey.